<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Ava Silver</title>
    <description>
      i'm ava silver (she/her). welcome to my corner of the internet!
    </description>
    <link>https://avasilver.dev</link>
    <lastBuildDate>04 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <item>
      <title>Transition: A Retrospective</title>
      <link>https://avasilver.dev/blog/transition</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://avasilver.dev/blog/transition</guid>
      <pubDate>22 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[<h1 id="transition-a-retrospective">Transition: A Retrospective</h1>
<p>Date: 2025-06-22</p>
<p>It’s been nearly five years now since I began really considering my
own gender and started transitioning, and seeing as both of my
girlfriends have written blog posts discussing transition and what it
has meant to them (<a href="https://miakizz.quest/posts/trans1/">Mia’s
post</a>, <a href="https://breq.dev/2025/06/22/gender">Brooke’s
post</a>), I figured I’d follow suit with a post of my own.</p>
<p>Brooke’s post starts off with: &gt; I’ve noticed that I can be far
too quick to assume that the experience of others matches my own.</p>
<p>And I’ve certainly been guilty of this as well, but realizing that
all three of our transitions (and feelings around it) have been quite
different, I figure it’s worth sharing mine as well. To be honest, it
can be a little intimidating to write about a subject like this, because
of how much there is to talk about – where even to begin? For this blog,
I’ll stick with the obvious place to begin: the beginning.</p>
<h2 id="the-beginning">The Beginning</h2>
<p>While gender dysphoria has been something I’ve dealt with at least
since puberty, I couldn’t really put my finger on what was wrong until I
started really looking – which began around five years ago. I had been
acquaintances with some trans folks before then, but had always been too
shy and afraid of asking personal questions to have anything really
click.</p>
<p>During the summer of 2020, peak quarantine, I reconnected with an old
friend of mine, and met his partner at the time, who was nonbinary and
starting to question their gender. It was through many many late nights
of hours-long conversing that I began to understand that gender was
something that I, too, could play with and take in whatever direction I
wanted.</p>
<p>I’ve never been one to make huge decisions all at once, and as such,
transition never really was an all or nothing situation for me. I began
with the simplest of things: letting a friend of mine paint my nails –
with simply a layer of top coat. While it was (objectively) such a small
thing, it symbolically meant much more to me. It was the first time I
had stepped out against the perceived lines of the gender prison I was
restricted to. And it felt wonderful!! I had no idea where I was really
going at the time, but I knew to trust my gut, and my gut said that it
was right. I then progressed, onto all kinds of colored nail polish, and
various makeup products. It was around winter break of 2020 that I begin
to realize that all these collective actions had a theme, one that I
then began to grapple with the reality of what all these “fun little
things” meant.</p>
<h2 id="labels-and-identity">Labels and Identity</h2>
<p>Rewinding a bit, as a boy, I had always felt that label Bisexual
never fully quite encapsulated the entirety of how I felt, but I had a
very difficult time pinning down why. I spent a long time thoroughly
analyzing the intricacies and qualia of my attraction, completely
oblivious of how my own gender plays into it. I went back and forth on
being aromantic, demisexual, and a variety of other microlabels. Whether
or not any of those actually apply to me, the exploration ended up
mostly just being my own distraction from the elephant in the room: my
gender. Unbeknownst to me, factors like gender envy, dysphoria and
anxieties about my own gender would have a much bigger role than I could
have anticipated in explaining how and why I feel the way I do.</p>
<p>In fact, in the midst of all this, I got some advice from a friend
that (unknowingly) pushed me to start transitioning: &gt; Don’t worry
about figuring everything out in your mind – just focus on doing what
feels right.</p>
<p>This mindset shift for me got me out of a loop of anxiety and
uncertainty, and helped me live in the moment and not worry about every
single detail. Living in this way has shaped my view on labels – that
they are helpful in helping you understand and validate your feelings,
but that they aren’t a requirement for you to start living your best
life. It is better to f*ck around now and find out later, than to never
f*ck around and never find out what you really want in life.</p>
<h2 id="end-of-beginning">End of Beginning</h2>
<p>Back to winter break of 2020, I had been trying things for months
without thinking about exactly why I was doing it, or what it all meant,
but that was starting to catch up with me. When I learned about HRT and
realized I wanted to try it, I knew I needed to find a justification to
my friends and family. It would be nice to live in a society where
people could do whatever they like with gender without justification,
but unfortunately we aren’t there yet. I ended up playing around with
the terms ‘Nonbinary’ and ‘Transfemme’ to try and categorize how I felt
to others, namely my parents. While this gave justification for my
desire to go on HRT, it came as a bit of a shock to my parents when I
mentioned that just a week after telling them that I was “questioning my
gender”.</p>
<p>This sparked a lot of intense conversation, discussion, and debate,
absolutely none of which I was ready for, emotionally or educationally.
Because this effectively put a block on my ability to start HRT, I began
on a search to look for other ways to explore the labels that I had now
attached to myself. My first real (semi-permanant) body modification,
beyond the aforementioned things, was dying my hair bright purple and
giving myself a crude undercut. While it wasn’t much, and arguably
didn’t actually make my presentation more femme, it was a freeing
departure from the logistics and planning blocking my desire for
HRT.</p>
<p>In spite of the logistics required for HRT (I wasn’t able to do
informed consent for reasons I won’t get into), I decided to try the
next feasible steps: new clothes, name, and pronouns. I ordered a skirt
online, and again, the rush of joy hit when I tried it on and gave it a
twirl. I narrowed down a list of names, asking my trans friends what
they thought fit me, and started off with they/them pronouns, although I
would occasionally ask my friends to try out ‘she’ pronouns. Luckily,
because I had already semi-intentionally surrounded myself with a group
of friends who would likely be receptive to my coming out, the coming
out process was completely painless, except for the excruciating anxiety
before hitting send on the message.</p>
<p>Following my gut, but still deeply unsure and nervous, I continued,
and with the support of some friends, went clothes shopping at the local
department store. Especially with the pain of being unable to alter my
body, having supportive friends (even if most of them were cis) that
could help with the other aspects of transition was something that
grounded me and kept me going, and is something I’ll always be grateful
for.</p>
<p>Especially with how much I had to assert myself to get where I wanted
to go, I was hardly certain that it was 100% the right move, and like
many trans people, I had uncertainty to face. How could I possibly be
certain that my feelings won’t change 5, 10, 25 years down the road? The
truth is, you really can’t. But like many other big decisions in life,
like choosing your major, getting married, or having kids, sometimes you
just have to take a leap of faith. And a leap of faith it certainly was.
It was terrifying and thrilling, but I kept myself grounded by keeping
in mind all the experiences over the last 20 years of my life that led
me to this point.</p>
<p>The beautiful thing about gender and transition is, you’re never
truly stuck. You can always make a change, and even a permanent change
just is part of your life and your story. One psychiatrist I met with
before HRT told me something that has stuck with me: &gt; Your gender is
like a canvas. Each choice you make in transition is another piece of
the canvas, and no matter what you end up doing later, you can always
add more to it as time goes on.</p>
<p>There is no absolutely right or wrong decisions, just
<em>decisions</em> you get to make and evaluate as you live them.</p>
<p>After six long months of back and forth, as well as plenty of
logistics and struggle, I was finally able to get on HRT. While you
might think that this would be a triumphant moment, it honestly just
felt overdue and like I was finally done with the very beginning of my
transition. Now I could finally begin the waiting period as estrogen
therapy reversed the damage done to my body over the last 5 years of the
wrong puberty.</p>
<p>But even after finally trying all the things I had wanted to try in
the beginning, ending that chapter, I still wasn’t sure exactly how to
place myself. I knew I definitely didn’t feel like a man, that was what
I was trying to escape. But I also knew that, at least based on
experience, presentation, and my place in society, I wasn’t simply a
woman. Because of this, I latched onto the label ‘transfem nonbinary’,
as it felt like, through the label, I could sort of give myself freedom
from strict labels, by using the more broad label ‘nonbinary’. At this
point in my life, I don’t consider myself to be nonbinary anymore, and
while you could call it a phase, it was a very very helpful phase for
me.</p>
<p>Being early in your transition as a trans woman is absolutely
terrifying. All the horrible stereotypes are targeted at you, and you
are just trying your best, not knowing what you’re doing, and to boldly
declare yourself a woman when there is still (understandably)
incongruence, is often met with much more backlash. For me, not having
the confidence to declare myself a woman, hell, not even being sure if I
am a woman, or what that fully entails, retreating to the more ambiguous
nonbinary label gave me the freedom I needed. As time went on, I became
more comfortable in the feminine presentation and gendered existence I
had created for myself, and while I never really had a “I am a woman”
moment, over time the term just became more and more comfortable.</p>
<h2 id="hindsight">Hindsight</h2>
<p>Now, five years out, and having completed numerous steps beyond what
I’ve listed here to further my transition, I’ve become much more
comfortable in my body, and have been able to live with so much more joy
and life than I ever had before. I’ve been able to encourage others to
take the difficult steps to begin down the same route, and grow into a
community that continues to thrive, despite the increasingly rampant
archaic legislation against trans existence. I’m more than happy to say,
that all those years ago, my gut was, without a shadow of a doubt,
unequivocally correct.</p>
<p>While many trans people may not approach transition the same way that
I did, it brings me joy to know that we all followed what we knew to be
right for us, and are better off for it. That knowledge gives me the
strength to fight for the trans children of the future, so they may have
(at least) the same opportunities that I had. 🏳️‍⚧️</p>]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coming Out</title>
      <link>https://avasilver.dev/blog/coming-out</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://avasilver.dev/blog/coming-out</guid>
      <pubDate>08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[<h1 id="coming-out">Coming Out</h1>
<p>Date: 2025-07-08</p>
<p>What is coming out? As a queer person, I am intimately familiar with
it. It has become almost a sacred thing in the queer community, and has
gained much notoriety from outside folks trying to understand the queer
experience. In a lot of ways, the queer experience, in media, often is
reduced to just the coming out experience. But despite that media and
representation, when it came to my own coming out moments, I could never
have anticipated how hard it would be.</p>
<p>It’s so easy to say “just get it over with”. But I’ve had many
friends struggle with their own coming out – some even delaying it
perpetually in the years I’ve known them. And it’s painful for me to see
them struggle, both because I care about them and want to see them
flourish as I have, but also because unlike a lot of media, I actually
understand how arduous it can be. It’s not to say that all coming out
has to be (or is) this way, I have friends who have had a wonderful
time! But in the majority of cases I’ve been a part of or observed, it’s
often difficult to get through, even when the people you’re coming out
to are self-proclaimed allies.</p>
<p>I remember the first time I decided to come out, it was after many
nights of trying to reason to myself if telling my parents would even be
worth it. For a long time, I had told myself I could just never come out
my whole life, and it would logically be the simplest way to live. But
this wasn’t a logical matter. At the time, I didn’t know why, but I knew
I needed to do it.</p>
<p>So one evening, I had gotten myself all psyched up, and decided that
during dinner, I was going to announce to my parents that I am Bisexual.
But as the conversation drew on, there never really came a perfect time,
like I had pictured in my head. In fact, when I then tried to imagine
what I would say when the time came, I drew a blank. How could I begin
to say something so important? I couldn’t just blurt out “I’m
Bisexual!”, it would sound crass and insincere. I needed to come up with
a way to preface it, so I’d have the best shot of them taking me
seriously and accepting me. But as things went on, I felt a sinking
disappointment in myself as I realized I wasn’t actually going to be
coming out that dinner, even though I had promised to myself that I
would.</p>
<p>It wasn’t actually until the next night or two where I decided to
tell my parents that I had something to announce <em>before</em> dinner.
This gave me the runway to take off and preface what I needed to say.
And as we sat down at the table, the impending conversation felt like a
brick in my stomach, a physical sensation that I knew to be all in my
head, but was so viscerally real it was impossible to ignore. In the
state of near paralysis, the words, as if molten lava, finally poured
out of my mouth. Then, even before my parents could say anything, came a
rush of relief. I don’t remember the exact words I used, in fact I don’t
think even I remembered them 5 seconds after I said them. I could go on
about how my parents responded, what they said, what I had hoped they’d
say, but honestly, it isn’t really even relevant. I realized that my
fear, my anxiety, the dread, were internal in a lot of ways. While
obviously the reaction I would get would affect me in a multitude of
ways, in a lot of ways, once the words poured out of me, things shifted,
from what I needed to do, to listening and deciding how to respond.</p>
<p>In that moment, I came to understand fundamental truths about coming
out: while it is a proclamation, more than that, it is about
vulnerability, about sharing a sensitive part of yourself with another
person, and having courage to trust that they will take care of that
sensitivity. Without vulnerability, “I am bisexual” is just a statement,
a boring fact.</p>
<p>And really, while that was a first real “coming out” for me, I had
experienced it in lesser ways many times before! Months prior, when I
still didn’t think I could ever come out to anyone, ever, a close friend
of mine James, after inviting me to lunch, came out to me as gay. It was
all that I needed to immediately have the trust and opportunity to come
out as well. And while it wasn’t as nerve-wracking as with my parents,
it still carried many of the same themes and meanings: vulnerability (in
this case on both sides), fear, and ultimately, connection.</p>
<p>But actually, the more I thought about it, I realized that even if
that was the first time I had come out as some form of queer, coming out
was a process I had encountered before, when at the age of thirteen, I
came out to my (christian) parents as an atheist. And while initially it
may feel like it’s not a “real” coming out, it has all the same key
elements, down to the reaction from my parents, in confusion and not
understanding how I could be this way, or what it means for me.</p>
<p>At this point in my life, I’ve now come out to various folks as
(chronologically):</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>atheist</li>
<li>bisexual</li>
<li>nonbinary</li>
<li>transgender</li>
<li>polyamorous</li>
</ol>
<p><br />
And even through it all, I still get a little nervous before having to
come out again. I was asked not too long ago, “how do you have so much
confidence in coming out?”, and like anything else in life, it comes
down to practice. Not practicing by yourself in the mirror, but by the
practice of doing. Even within each identity, it’s always a continuous
process of coming out to all the different people in your life. Each
coming out is obviously different, but by continuously coming out you
gain more comfortability in it. Sometimes it can seem like in gaining
comfort, you lose vulnerability, and as such you no longer need to “come
out”. But, at least in my experience, it’s not that you become less
vulnerable, but that vulnerability becomes easier and more
comfortable.</p>
<p>That comfortability in being vulnerable is something that is
foundational all the relationships in my life, and has helped me
flourish and grow as a person in ways I never knew possible. While
coming out can be scary, in the end I’m glad I’ve gone through it so
much, not for other’s sake, but for my own.</p>]]></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>To Be a Mother</title>
      <link>https://avasilver.dev/blog/to-be-a-mother</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">https://avasilver.dev/blog/to-be-a-mother</guid>
      <pubDate>04 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <description><![CDATA[<h1 id="to-be-a-mother">To Be a Mother</h1>
<p>Date: 2025-10-04</p>
<p> </p>
<p><em>Dedicated to: my mother Susan</em></p>
<p> </p>
<p>To be a mother is to be human</p>
<p>To sometimes fail to connect to your child, no matter how hard you
try</p>
<p>To fuck things up, even when your intentions are pure</p>
<p>To try too hard, to care too much – pushing away your child in the
process</p>
<p> </p>
<p>To be a mother is to be nurturing</p>
<p>To share your most cherished moments, to help your child
understand</p>
<p>To gift your favorite music, to have it become your child’s favorite,
too</p>
<p>To teach, to understand, and to forgive</p>
<p> </p>
<p>To be a mother is hard</p>
<p>To be underappreciated</p>
<p>To be overburdened</p>
<p>To try your best, even if it’s not enough</p>
<p> </p>
<p>To be a mother is everything</p>
<p>To find a new purpose in life, for worse and for better</p>
<p>To have your child be your whole world, but for it to take them time
to understand, if they ever truly do</p>
<p>To watch your child grow, knowing they’ll make their own mistakes and
learn things in their own time</p>
<p> </p>
<p>To be a child is to grow up</p>
<p>To obey your mother, and break her rules</p>
<p>To eventually understand, and see her as human</p>
<p>To appreciate her care, and to forgive her mistakes</p>
<p> </p>
<p>And to one day repeat the cycle, doing your best to learn from both
her successes and mistakes ❤️</p>
<p> </p>
<hr />
<p> </p>
<p><em>This poem was inspired by my friend <a
href="https://dimabelle.substack.com/">Dima</a> suggesting I try my hand
at poetry, and recently watching Lady Bird</em></p>]]></description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
